software engineering radio episode 93
lessons learned from architectural
reviews with Rebecca Bob Spock
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the
program
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio this time we
are at the cello conference in Denmark
once again and we're talking to Rebecca
versus Brock today about lessons learned
from architecture reviews so Rebecca
welcome to the show thank you glad to be
here
very nice and why don't you introduce
yourselves or listeners know who you are
well I'm best known for having invented
responsibility driven design which is a
way of thinking about organizing systems
and dividing responsibilities amongst
objects but in my recent travels I've
spent a lot of time looking at
architectures and sorting those out
which is the purpose of what we're going
to talk today
the reason travels hints add that you're
probably a travelling consultant yes
exactly exactly
okay so yeah so the topic today will be
architecture reviews we already had well
a more conceptual discussion last year
at gel with targis Manila school so this
year is gonna be probably a more much
more practical view on it lessons
learned sounds to be practical so why
don't you give us a quick overview of
what it's all about and then we'll talk
about details well from my perspective
I've been involved in two ways as one
who has obviously as a consultant gone
in and tried to review an architecture
with teams I've got asked to do that and
so I've learned things about how people
tell me things and how to really find
out what's really going on and then the
other aspect is as a developer lead
designer presenting material for reviews
so I'm I get both sides of the coin
mm-hm
okay so that's let's get started the
first thing that that we have in our
script are on your slides or whatever
it's a statement says beware of the
technical stack on us what does that
suggest I have an idea but you have an
idea well in some sense I'm thinking of
a specific review where I went in and
the only thing that was there that the
chief technical architect would talk
about was the technical stack
and the beauty of it and the picture on
the slide is of Zen stones nightly
nicely stacked up and arranged in a
beautiful and there was no substance
behind the technical stack so the
technical stack does not make the
architecture and I find many times the
technical nuances are what intrigues
smart architects and they worry about
the wrong things so just to get it clear
technical stack you mean I use WebLogic
XYZ and then I have a web service
communication to the other guy and we're
using people yeah and there's our
messaging strategy and ogee the real
problem was to unify two domain models
and we didn't even think about that okay
and and so it's easy to get in our field
I think any smart architect likes to
consider the latest technology yes and
the whole stack is beautiful but the
solving of the real problem might be
uglier yeah yep actually I've also
that's one of my things always talk
about that you should talk also about
the conceptual aspects of an
architecture is it asynchronous
synchronous stateless they say for these
kinds of things they're not just on real
technical tool details and it's easy to
latch on to technical tool details
because there's all kinds of things we
can dig into as opposed to the other
qualities as well performance
scalability usability all those things
No the other thing is visualize the
benefits so probably first make people
happy of what you have and then and then
start criticizing on what what does that
mean oh well in actual fact I think if
you're trying to present your
architecture to someone that we can
present them very technical detailed
descriptions and draw nice pictures but
if they don't know what it's going to do
for them and why it's going to be a good
architecture then we haven't spoken to
their heart and I'm thinking in
particular again flipping the putting on
a different hat as when I worked on a
telco integration framework and we
worked on great models and presented a
prototype but the key thing that sold it
to the management was the visual
the benefits of the fact is we had this
don't call us we'll call you
architecture with an adapter and so
you'd have common adapters two common
systems that we were trying to integrate
and that would really reduce the costs
of integration of new systems as we were
acquiring them and with all our
beautiful architecture if they didn't
understand and could visualize why what
we were pushing was important then and
when they did they got very excited yeah
so we needed to find a way to
communicate the essence that was really
going to be you know the important thing
no and well if you do a review how do
you find the right people to whom you
show what you have and also who do how
do you find the people who are actually
a good good candidates to tell about the
architecture what about how do you find
out which people who get involved well
in its again from from both perspectives
if you find that you need to have a
technical review obviously you need
technical people involved and it's good
to have have a different perspective
than just people like you so if I'm
integrating a system it would be nice to
have other people that are you know I'm
integrating with who are experts in that
area or the technology and and actually
I think we're pretty good at finding
technical reviewers but what we don't
find is that sometimes the product
owners and the people who really are
going to demand those things of our
systems if we just had them there then
they could tell us the right stories
that we needed to support we we like to
create things and if we over engineer
things because we think they want it
then we can get in trouble so so maybe
another term for this would be
stakeholder integration get all the
stakeholders and and make sure everybody
has a say in the thing and stakeholders
aren't just I'd say product sponsors or
someone who are buying it but they're
people who maybe in the marketing that
are specifying features if we're
developing products as well yep so in
some sense if you do an architectural
review you're kind of the increase
right so you go there and you have to
make sure you're actually getting to the
point and finding the issues if there
are any so asking the right question is
probably a big deal yes and asking the
right questions doesn't necessarily say
we're not looking for is the
architecture good yes or no I don't
think those binary question those are
really what we're doing we're probing
for doesn't mean the real
characteristics we must have assuming
they're specified somewhere if they
aren't then I would say there's a little
bit of problem or a little bit of
investigation about what the real you
know qualities that we're trying to
produce and so that leads you into as a
reviewer if someone doesn't ask you or
doesn't present everything you need to
be prepared to ask those questions you
need to propose propose and probe and
and uncover the things that may not be
said wouldn't it be nice if I had all
this documentation and and I just dived
into a review and it was easy but it's
never that way so let's get specific
what are so how do you what you know
other some stereotypes or idioms that
you can use to think about what kind of
questions to ask well I think that as as
a question asker I always feel like
there's a old TV show about this
detective called Columbo it's a u.s. TV
show and he was this unassuming
gentleman he wore a rumpled clothing and
he was always basically well I don't
know but maybe you know can you tell me
so so in actual fact I am NOT making
judgments but I might evaluate well how
good do you think this is going to be
right when kind of is that really so so
reaffirming when someone makes a claim
that maybe you know is outrageous but in
another way coming back and saying well
is that is that really the case right I
heard you say this but do you do you
mean that I'm I don't know this but
maybe may
is that really so so you could ask you
know accuracy questions or are there
complete is that all oh gee that doesn't
sound like there's enough there so so
there's all these kinds of ways of
asking questions in a way I think it's
not just asking probing questions but
asking them in a way it gets people to
open up and not necessarily i if i'm
conducting a review being so judgmental
that i'm trying to get them to open up
another technique that i like to use is
that i reformulate what they just said
in my words maybe draw a little diagram
and try to understand what they did say
the same thing in my world and then just
see whether that kind of is compatible
to make sure I understood it correctly
absolutely
and in some sense when I'm doing this I
have to go in there without although I'm
a threat as a consultant I'm an external
source of agitation we get right in any
way you evaluate their work yeah exactly
and so in some sense I need to also
validate that their whatever they're
telling me is they're telling me the
truth and and that I just want to
understand and help me you know clarify
my understanding of what you're doing I
think that's a lot of what I do yeah so
you basically try to make them think you
you you you you ask questions where you
hope that it makes them think of what
they just said and what they maybe
should have thought about when they
built the system and hopefully did and
sometimes yeah there's a subtle subtle
subtle art to that I would say and so
you know why did you do that that way
what's the purpose of something oh I can
understand
well did you consider you know so again
in a gentle way I guess it rather than a
harsh way of and I can have them reveal
limitations that way that they may not
have been at first willing to talk about
or even thought about I mean were they
really aware of that well maybe not but
so I bring my context and background
into it as well yes yeah so how
component is it that you as a reviewer
or actually understand the kind of
system they built being beat the domain
or maybe some of the architectural
technical issues do you think everybody
can review every art well every good
reviewer can review any kind of
architecture or do you need a connection
to the kind of stuff they're doing in
addition to it being software well
that's a good question because in some
sense I've been asked to review a
variety of different things of which
I've had no no knowledge of but from my
general ancient background of you know
over 20 years of software development
and systems I can usually draw some
connections for example and enterprise
java application certainly has some
common nuts and bolts that I'm familiar
with but I think it's fair to say where
you're not competent to review so you
don't just want to dive in and you know
concurrent real-time embedded systems is
not my forte
yeah well although I have done technical
fuse for that but I do have some
background in that too so I don't think
you want to overextend your your
knowledge but you know if if you don't
understand the technology then it's it's
somewhat difficult yeah right yeah
that's my experience too although
sometimes I think new technologies are
just the old stuff with a new name and
you can I mean so is a good example I
mean if you've done distributed systems
well it's not that big a deal
it's not that different and if you're
talking about message orchestration yeah
well there's other things that we did
before so so yeah yeah no it's but there
is new nuances and accumulated
technology things but not everything
about an architecture is technical
exactly yeah that's what we talked about
before the next thing that's on our list
is probably to to judge how big you
organized the review like if you're a
two-person project you shouldn't come
with a five person review team so how do
you size the review to the architecture
well it's really a matter of
which they want to know about the
architecture and if it's a small change
if you will let's say an incremental
release or I'm just reimplemented the
same things on a new hardware platform
so it's not always just the team size
but it's the size of the architectural
change size of the problem yes that
they're trying to solve and so I'm
thinking back to people who want to
really get it right to may start up and
think they need this big formal review
cycle but they have to really consider
is this a major architectural
significance is this a new thing or is
it just some incremental so that's one
consideration a review team of one or
two people can actually do quite a lot I
wouldn't think that the size of a
project is so important as the size of
the architectural change and impact you
know how much disk open what you need to
do particularly if you're building
something that is designed to have a 10
year lifecycle or 15 year lifecycle you
know being like a Egyptian pyramids
lasting a long time requires more care
and review than otherwise yeah it's a
thing if you're building a platform for
product lines a different thing than if
you just hang your web application well
yes yes yeah another metric that I like
to use is also simply how much money do
you would like would you like to spend I
mean I've had cases where they said you
know we like to have this Erika to
architecture review done and we well we
three days I think three days should we
don't have more money so that also
answers the question well yes and that
that's that's true they'll get what they
they find in that time frame and so in
that case you really have to focus on
what are the key values that you want me
to explore because I could wallow in the
review all over the place you know look
all over the system so so how detailed
do you expect your honest a this review
ii or who do the thing you review or
your
in that sense how specifically do you
want them to ask you specific questions
that you try to find out
do you just go in there and say well as
review the architecture or how specific
are the goals of the architecture itself
specified typically it actually depends
on how experienced they are at doing
reviews and some people would like to
follow a process like something like the
hm you know the sei well let's look at
the quality scenarios and growth
scenarios and and know Rebecca do come
in and help us examine those things and
those are rare actually it's my
experience and most people say well
we're doing something that's this size
and we know we have some problems or
concerns here so you tell me what your
concerns are as a consultant I can come
in and then probe around and then I may
decide that I need another colleague or
two to help and I can counter propose so
much money well this is what you'll get
yeah sure but maybe we need to look
deeper yeah so leveling the playing
field I guess is crucial I mean if you
have this this this architect who feels
intimidated by the review team who comes
in and and you know like as I said one
architect five reviewers then there is
something wrong so there's also I guess
this psychological issue well it's
really the case and that even within a
company let's say not having an outside
consultant come in but if I have to go
in front of a number of people and
present my architectural ideas and it's
a it's a big big threat and maybe
there's politics involved yeah and of
stuff and so in actual fact if you if
companies do set aside and get some
consistency amongst it it can make it so
the expectations aren't that you're
going to go in front of the Spanish you
know the Inquisition if you will yeah
but that it's a set of peers that are
helping architects Express and do it in
a I guess a non-political way but a
supportive review then that can kind of
make it less intimidating and more
effective for companies here I think
that's maybe also one of the reasons why
external
viewers are brought in because they are
not involved in politics that's a good
point but someone politically brought us
in you know someone brought us in for a
reason okay someone has some worry right
some concern right so but we are not we
don't have a vested interest in a
particular outcome unless we're let's
say a technologist who works for a
product that they're having employed as
part of their architects in which case
you're not a good reviewer I would guess
about that well that's actually that's
actually not not always the case when we
were at interviewing and getting
reviewers for this telco product that I
worked on we purposefully asked the
technologists when one of the external
reviewers to be the server product
because we were early implementation of
this Java server tech and so but we
didn't expect them to make all the
comments about other things right they
were specifically there to help you with
their system yes there's what are rainy
days scenarios what happens when things
go wrong when one of the things that
sometimes people ask you in a review is
let's make sure we understand the limits
of our system and and what it can really
do we're investing a lot so can you
please help us understand and articulate
the limits and the constraints and have
you have our technology addressed it but
I find that sometimes they have a tough
time saying what will really happen you
know how much do they really want to
invest in in recovery or performance
scalability when life is bad you know
when when the architecture is really you
know strained and pushed to its limits
yeah which typically means that several
things go wrong at the same time so you
have several risks that kind of stack
onto each other to really get to the
problem like any accident right
absolutely and so it's really kind of
interesting when you do have those
situations and I'm thinking of again
another
Elco system that I worked on is that you
had to what was really important in that
case was articulating the limits
although it was it would roll over to
fail over to another computing system we
had to say well two faults two major
faults at the same time as where we
stopped yeah because there's only so
much investment but until they
articulated that the architects didn't
and when they wanted to make it more
reliable and they were they needed to
know the boundaries and so expressing
the limits to the rainy day are bad
things go wrong can really help people
do that but but we have trouble stopping
and knowing what's enough either it's
too hard so we don't try to do anything
in our architecture recover or it's we
want to do so much that we don't know
when to stop
right yeah yeah and again it goes back
to this requirements thing I think well
I have not worked much in the telco area
or something but I think it's very hard
to make a customer say well how many
nines do you need after the dot what
what are you willing which risks are you
willing to take with regards for example
to uptime so getting precise
requirements in order to know where to
stop it's probably not that trivial also
for a review room well it for I would
say for hardware related systems it is
easier to get those numbers but then
from a software standpoint the software
that's influencing the really how many
nines you get then it becomes a matter
of well how much effort can we expend
because to get to that next nine is you
know an order order of magnitude but
also people don't like to talk about
failure in recovery exist in general
that's not we think about requirements
in terms of what something should do not
how should it recover yeah and oh but
yes it must but they don't like to talk
a lot about that yeah in actual fact
when you're talking about risk compound
one of the other problems that people
have is if they don't know exactly the
probability of a failure or a
probability of something happening and
you're trying to architect or present
options based on a spectrum of options
that we must do
they tend to favor things that are known
probabilities and latch onto those and
discuss those or things that where it's
not so clear and that's natural human
nature if something appears to be a
better situation then they're gonna if
we're presenting a range of all
architectural alters yeah yeah something
that appears more certain even though it
has less benefit is easy to select or
want to have than something that's going
to have big benefit but it's not so
certain that we'll get that benefit and
why is that a problem or why is that bad
or well if I'm an architect and I'm
really proposing something if I can
offer facts call and create facts again
flipping around to this point over
concrete facts that absolutely
demonstrate that this will have you know
thirty five percent thirty five point
eight percent better then it's far
better if something well I think it will
but I'm not certain and sometimes with
new technology it's very difficult for
us to give those numbers and so we give
sometimes probabilities and people don't
react well if they're trying to choose
amongst options for things I think are
going to be good and trust me sometimes
they should question but sometimes if
something seems so certain they'll pick
some choice that involves let's say
technology or even software development
risk that isn't going to have a big
benefit big enough benefit because it's
the easy certain thing to do and
sometimes we have to push for more risky
things but if there's more uncertainty
around it then people don't like that
they're gonna back away just human
nature
so as an architect if I'm trying to sell
an idea that's the point yeah yeah the
more facts I have the better I'm better
I am able to to compel people and facts
are either experience reports or maybe
metrics measurable yeah prototypes
measurable measurable types of things
but if I'm having to conjecture a bit
that's when I start to be a little bit
to you no doubt it and there's a lot of
risks that we don't know and a lot of
precisely what you know why are you
doing something I mean we we know it
will be better but we can't quantify
things as clearly as we might like to to
make our argument and then there's the
case if you're you know talking about
people listening to your ideas as an
architect if if they perceive that
something is not certain and I've had
managers myself react this way and you
need to test this either they totally
ignore any risk or they totally are in
fear of that risk happening so they're
switched from either they totally ignore
the probability and leap ahead if
they're if they want or they become
paralyzed by it
and and that's that's actually a
dangerous thing to when you're you know
the risks of an architecture a reason
they heard the podcast where some
scientists said that humans are really
bad in working with probability in
general so that's maybe that's one of
the reasons that they kind of see this
number it's closer to zero than 100 or
the other way around and then I kind of
flip to this oh it's going to be bad yes
right well and it depends upon whether
they're a eternal pessimist or an
optimist yeah and depending upon the
company if you will in the circumstance
it maybe is beneficial to be a little
bit risk adverse
you know if you look at certain
companies they make their business off
of being risk adverse and others on the
other hand do you have to take those
risks okay information bias well so when
I'm presenting information that supports
an idea we've been talking about the
reason why people sometimes flip over
binary as they become fearful but what
the other problem can be that even if
I'm proposing an architectural idea and
giving some credible evidence that it's
never enough we ask for more data oh
that was a nice prototype but can you
show what's going to happen here and
they keep asking and asking because
they're not going to commit to our
architecture and so in that case it's a
very difficult Channel
an architect to get them over that
hurdle and take your new idea so in some
sense you have to try very hard to
present facts in new ways and convince
people maybe by even saying well our
competitors are doing this so we should
do something else okay
when you're building systems these days
there's typically at least in the
enterprise world there's typically
always legacy stuff involved so there's
always the existing systems with which
we have to merge our integrator which
you have to evolve so that I guess there
are some specific risks and also then as
a consequence some specific points you
should address as a reviewer oh
absolutely and I think actually Eric
Evans strategic design which he's going
to be talking about at this conference
is one way to address that in that if
we're merging existing systems perhaps
it's not just the technology that we
should be concerned about but are their
domain models and data that needs to be
merged and the platform isn't just one
isolated silo that we just bang into
another way and in in some sense merging
existing technologies isn't just the
only problem there's the operational
risks of of how do I get the systems
convert it and working together and to
me those things can be showstoppers on
many reviews and actually if I'm just
focusing on the new technology then all
these other merging of
customer needs of platforms if domain
models of data can be a you know huge
problem that people don't recognize
their consequence yeah and another thing
when you integrate several systems is
that you often throw away one of them
more or less and people are often
reluctant if they have invested a lot of
work into it their baby you know it's
their baby and in some sense we spent a
lot for that baby and we bought that
baby from another company let's say we
merged a company even and and then we
must do something with it right
where's in actual fact it probably would
have been better again to take the
functionality and re-implement it rather
than try to bolt systems together but
once I've invested right in that that
technology or that other system I want
to try to use it you know it's like in
some sense I think that executives think
that it's less cost to integrate but
they don't understand deep issues yeah
exactly
another thing that comes to mind is that
many people actually likes well the
problem is if you promised a big benefit
but it's far away people won't maybe let
you actually do it so you have to to
small steps and show small benefits and
so in that case it isn't the case that
we want to just you know throw that away
and re implement it but we we'd like to
merge the system gradually over time or
do things like that and that takes an
understanding of a longer term set of
steps but if we don't break it down into
smaller steps of how to get there then
and if we as architects just say well
here's the end state and it's so far
away that's so much easier for them to
just take the low-hanging fruit the easy
thing and never get to where we need to
do to be integrated it's really
integrated and so as an architecture
review consultant I guess my job
sometimes has been to point out what
everyone knows are the problems but they
just don't like to talk about so much
and it's not just technology it's
haddaway handle technology and how do I
merge designs and how do I really
benefit the most out of out of syncs yep
okay let's look a little bit about how
you describe decisions because I mean as
the that's the I reviewed well the one
whose architecture is going to be
reviewed you will have to explain why
you did things the way you do because
that's one of the main points of
architectural reviews I guess so what
can you say about how do you actually
plain ideas and decisions to a reviewer
what do you want to hear well I think
there's it depends on your audience
are you having someone who's going to
give you a constructive set of
commentary back and that's what you'd
like or are you trying to sell something
to someone and they say yes I'll buy it
and those are two different kinds of
reviewers and if I'm wanting to have a
constructive thought-out
thoughtful review I think there's one
pattern and if I'm trying to sell it I
might want to put a little slant on it a
bit differently and so I as a reviewer I
want to make clear that usually I'm not
I you know as an external reviewer I'm
not buying or selling
I'm just getting a judgement and and I'm
reflecting back things that you may
reveal to me so I'm going to ask you
questions about what requirements drove
you to it and why what things aren't you
going to consider because we could find
fault with every we as we've talked
about earlier with almost anything so
what were the limits that you designed
to or proposed in certain aspects of
your architecture and what give me a
give me a set of your benefits and
disadvantages because let's let's
consider them I may from my experience
that isn't the same as yours be able to
give you some ideas where I've seen
elsewhere so I can you know give you
some insights and if you're honest about
it again for a constructive reviewer if
there were things that you were not
certain about and you wanted me to
reflect upon well then tell me and so
that so that's one pattern for a a
constructive thoughtful person who isn't
you know gonna say yes no I'm gonna slam
you but they're going to give you
valuable feedback to improve the
architecture so on the other hand if you
have someone who is gonna be a little
bit more judgmental you may start out
with the things that limited
Arkan
iterations and then here's what we did
and we ruled out these things because of
those facts and here's what we're
recommending sell sell sell that's a
different approach that's a little
different approach something that I like
to use not in all to set an architecture
but just in order to document the single
decisions it's actually the pattern form
right you know the pattern a pattern is
also like a single piece of information
that is well described with problem
solution context and so on I think
that's also a good pattern to describe
any kind of decision and information so
that's also maybe an alternative so
that's actually interesting on our telco
integration framework where I got
external reviewers for we actually did
document our design decisions that way
and we had like key ten maybe key
decisions that drove us and we did did
use that and it I want I wasn't thinking
so much of patterns at the time but it
just seemed like a good way to explain
it but you're right it does match the
pattern sometimes the pattern form is
just a good way X to to explain well now
the other thing though that was slightly
different other than the pattern form
was again we were looking for feedback
so not just saying what the forces were
but also the issues that we wanted to
address so we wanted to leave it open
for someone to comment on mmm so how do
you work with biases that people have I
mean be them be they political or you
know there's this web service guy who
want to do everything with web services
sort of this Gregor Hope a who wants to
do everything with messaging so whatever
you do they're kind of biased toward
certain solutions how do you say or
aspects that aspects rule the world
they're they're really cool yeah and not
everyone shares the same biases and if
you latch on to an idea you think it's
really great I think it's it's really
hard to overcome biases or
predispositions right if I've done
something a certain way then I I tend to
follow that cow path we pave the cow
path as you say yeah
and in some sense the first thing to
realize is that you have biases too I
mean I do so
yes small talk is one of my favorite
biases right so so in a matter of fact
recognizing that people will naturally
it's not good or bad but it's just my
easy non-thinking reaction to something
and then to recognize that I have to
point them out if I'm going to or subtly
manipulate them yeah and that's not
selling its subtly manipulating it so
the information that they should be
seeing is more evident to them to
overcome their biases for them yep hmm
okay the next big issue is of course how
do you make sure if you give an advice
that people actually care and follow it
so you have to be convincing also as a
reviewer because you have to make them
do what you think is good well you
should at least well you want to make
like you can't make anyone do anything
as an external reviewer but you'd like
to make it clear that there are things
that they should do and it's there if
they don't do it here's what you think
about it and so in actual fact I've
learned that in order to again not be
threatening but be realistic yeah to
break down what I do into
recommendations versus suggestions and
observations so an observation if you if
you stack up a number of observations
well maybe they could draw some
conclusions that but I you know not
everything do I want to do that so I
limit the time that I do the really big
recommendations I can have a number of
suggestions but big recommendations
should should come out and and the other
observations they can draw their their
conclusions from so what is saying is
for the really important things that you
really think are mission-critical you
give specific recommendations Pacific
recommendations and as concretely as I
can supported by evidence because again
there are those people that say
fact-finding and so if I can even use
the words that I heard in a review or
samples of code if they're showing
thanks
so I can support it with evidence but
oftentimes the people that are reading
or looking at listening in to your
recommendations and I usually write rick
written recommendation want to know
what's the heavy hitter items the most
important and how do i support it with
evidence and then all these other things
you know like well those those are nice
it's actually interesting now after you
actually did the review as a reviewer
now you become kind of the architect
because now you have to communicate or
sell your let's say changes or your
changed architectural base in your
review your recommendations so whenever
you do an architectural review you also
have to play the role of the architect
that's an interesting point and and in
some sense I would say that I'm not the
architect but I'm also not the casual
observer anymore and so I am someone
who's saying given my wisdom and my
insight here's how I might adjust your
architecture know so it's it's a careful
line I've seen some architecture
reviewers go way over to just damming
and you know telling it's bad in
whatever whereas if you're having it
trying to have an impact you just need
to focus on here's the key things I
think must change and why yep in some
sense I think that if you adopt a triage
mentality when you're trying to make
recommendations when someone walks in in
a disaster and there's a number of
people that are injured or their spots
in the architecture that aren't you know
quite so you know the triage basically
says there are things we can do
something about
so they tie a green you know a orange or
yellow ribbon around it if it's serious
if it's dead and it's hopeless they tire
black ribbon around it and if it's green
like it's maybe a little problem but
nothing right then they they're whack
they're walking wounded that don't need
immediate attention so again it's again
trying to make sure that the most
important things get emphasized and and
the other things can
not everything has to be addressed so
how do i how do you persuade people to
to actually do that these things well I
as I said I have a written presentation
usually that I do but I also like to
review my presentation with the key
stakeholders before I I deliver it as
well so I'm saying here's the things I'm
going to say and then who's should I
really target this report to so that
they listen so for example I may bring
in a VP of engineering may bring me in
okay but he really wants the the CTO to
hear the message and so in some sense
I'm not trying to blindside the person
who brought me in to do the review I'm
trying to support and and discuss with
them and so in some sense then I package
it and this sounds like marketing
doesn't it but so that the person who's
the primary target of the change or the
recommendations hears it and they may
not hear exactly what they wanted to
hear Oh everything was rosy so so I have
to make sure that they agree with my
assessment and then presented in a way
that perhaps raised some of those issues
that they weren't comfortable with
hearing before they might have fixed on
something and said oh yes we're okay
we're great in this area right and then
you have to get them unstuck on on that
point perhaps and so it takes some
convincing
now I unless I live with a company after
I do a review I don't always get to
choose you know to make sure that they
hear all of what I say but I do my best
I do my best
sometimes they they don't listen to what
you say so they're gonna try to seek out
information that supports their pre held
view and that's a very difficult
challenge as a as an architect to do
well they paid for me to come in and and
talk to them alright they they paid for
me to spend a week or maybe even two
weeks going and look working with
technical staff and if I present them
enough evidence and they don't
they say well you're pretty harsh on us
and then they don't take my call to
action there's not much I can do except
for saying I did my honest assessment no
so it's I can't fix the world but I can
point out the most critical things to
consider so shouldn't yeah so is it yeah
so you probably even shouldn't feel
really responsible of having these
things implemented except if you're also
going to be brought in to actually
implement things but otherwise you're
basically you're point you're you're
missin mission is to point out what the
problems are and give recommendations
and that's it and that's and that's it
in a way that they will hear and so you
do have to again you know listen to who
is this reporter this review for and
oftentimes it's for me has been I'm
presenting a number of issues to the
technical staff and architects they
would they tend to have no problem
listening to me it's usually the
executives higher up where they may have
to make some tough decisions that it's
that it's more difficult so how much of
actually and you present the result of
your review or written or actual
presentation I probably do both so how
much of that is psychology and marketing
as opposed to hard facts well I think
it's a blend and the hard facts have to
be there my experience as a basis but
it's not enough it's not enough and in
some sense if all I did was present hard
facts they they probably wouldn't pay me
so much because I Despero technical and
so putting a spin on it in a way that
has reflected that I understand both
their mission their marketplace and
don't just focus on one thing but try to
fit in to their context Mike my comments
you know has it has a bigger impact so
in some sense I have to develop a
relationship with a variety of
stakeholders in order to have the impact
that I'd like in review and since
sometimes those stakeholders are on
different sides of the table that can be
quite a challenge that can be quite a
challenge it's I don't know
whether it's a good thing or not but
when at the end of a review when both
the architects product marketing and
engineering are happy with me I I think
I've done my job yes they not may not be
happy with the magnitude of a
recommendation but at least they they
felt like I heard their concerns and and
I think that yeah and I was fair but not
dismissive of little problems yeah so
they're appreciative in that way now do
they act that's another question okay so
this brings us to the end of our
discussion is there anything else you
want to say that we forgot or any like
words of wisdom towards the end well I I
actually think that as a as a company or
a product development group or a IT
group that sometimes you do need that
external perspective and so you know
external reviewers are good I'm not
saying this just for having a you know
no more consulting but on the other hand
if you're doing that that you ought to
consider that what's the next step you
need to I I'm very frustrated you know
by people who take reviews and say well
that was nice now let's go find another
reviewer who might tell us what we want
to hear I've heard that you know other
people who do architecture refuse and in
some sense if you're investing in this
then you should invest in some solutions
too exactly that was the prefix of the
the preload the foreword that I put on
to my the last review I did because I
was skeptical about whether my customer
would actually do what I said and
actually rate is that you know you pay
me you better at least consider it
seriously what I say and so and if
they're not then I suppose it's their
problem but it but in actual fact I
don't want to be part of their problem
I've ever done III I don't come in there
with my agenda yeah so let me ask one
last thing that just came to my mind
there is this thing about code reviews
so P teams do internal code reviews to
include
the quality of the code but also to well
to make the reviewers aware of what's
happening do you think it's a good idea
if you have a large organization to have
the teams to architecture reviews
between or among themselves so every
architecture team is also a reviewer of
other architectures that's to see both
sides of the coin I actually think that
if you build an architecture practice
that that's one of the fundamental
things to do and so large companies that
I know that are successful actually do
this and in some sense then you need to
have this culture that says when we make
commentary we're not trying to compete
or those kind of things but how do I
develop a supportive culture and and I
think it really helps because there
isn't just one best architecture and if
we're doing product lines or we're doing
enterprise applications certain things
may demand different choices and you
know people make choices that change
over time so so developing that
community of practice in larger
organizations is really important then
they don't need us so much as
consultants you know as if they develop
their own review culture and that would
be just fine by me but they need to know
how to communicate and that's that's a
lot of skill you'd find too often too
often yes and they also need to know in
some sense how to give a realistic
presentation of both benefits and risks
in a way that isn't going to turn people
off or snow them with too much dazzling
technical brilliance okay Rebecca thanks
for being on the show thank you very
much I enjoyed it yeah very good here is
a message from our sponsor hello he
isn't Andrew stone Christian vice from
the fimo
Pazuzu sophist understand long Jade who
you and Victor met excellent octave to
and Java a foul
I've coached retainer brings to engine
food biases to matter specify software
to evict first ellipse to i'll
specialness on also GRE also is my
vision I affirm as well as a lasagna of
munch my never mousse anything about our
design would be 215 BC from soon yet
while he was a dancer in China's
characteristic home versus a Pagani
that's your own miss keep me so Clara
here I hear she stopped one on man the
calm Kazakh Dumas yet Allah doesn't does
so no in the efficacy of directors Moses
there was a zoo there was an also key an
intrusion the undersides if you orders
my female fired you know English
transmission lines in her heart skeet
ears also evenly a Cup semi-finals
Andrew Liveris AG other objects on
whispers on about was a very sad but he
can spin zone that's fine it's just
he had a steam I worked life balance
host usually embed as we skied Vicki
soo-hyun Holy Father does eyes inside
like outside is as key - a key or Tom
not a bad set of right so are so the
finish another internal to go and thank
vice whether from all social be done and
we as a harm the situation the authority
of new prisons and abortion my team we
found water on I found for communicate
zone of zebras on the home guns form
fleeing on a famous a good holiday
finished items milk discard Canelo's
Ziva chief Starke Ryan which we fight
and we convey the spectrums that coast
of philosophy mother cleanest the
appointment of Danny be Baba Rama wine
and VBB was appointing
and thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and Su radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle